Guide to the Special Collections Research Center oral history collection, 1972-2016 MS0371
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Special Collections Research Center oral history collection
1972-2016
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Anderson, G. David
Deering, Mary Jo
MS0371
26.5 Linear Feet 11 document boxes, 1 slim document box, 7 cassette tape boxes, 9 record center cartons, and digital objects.
The George Washington University Oral History Program was begun by Mary Jo Deering and others in the early 1970s. Since that time, oral histories have been conducted by a number of individuals and projects represented in this collection. This collection consists primarily of oral histories conducted by or about George Washington University, although it also contains administrative files related to the oral history programs, and a significant amount of documentary material on school desegregation and the Rosemary Hills controversy.
Box R1
Box R2
Box R3
Box R4
Acquisition Information
Whenever it is known, acquisition data is included at the series or item level.
Historical Note
The George Washington University Oral History Program was begun by Mary Jo Deering and others in the early 1970s. Situated in the university library, this program appears to have had both teaching and collecting aims, as it engaged in large documentation projects on current local issues, and also taught participants how to conduct and transcribe oral histories. In 1976, Deering and Barbara Pomeroy published a booklet titled "Transcribing Without Tears: A Guide to Transcribing and Editing Oral History Interviews."
The largest, and possibly the first, project of the Oral History Program was to document ongoing and recent events around the desegregation of schools in Montgomery County, Maryland. This project was conceived broadly, and included the collection of a significant body of small publications and clippings related to desegregation both locally and nationally. Around this same time, the program also conducted a series of 18 interviews with University Historian Elmer Louis Keyser on a range of topics related to GW history.
This first GW Oral History Program program ended in the early 1980s, having failed to secure grant funding for additional projects, including one on DC's Wolf Trap Theater.
Contemporaneously with this oral history program, a Medical Center Oral History Committee was formed which identified, supervised, and collected oral histories from faculty, staff, and alumni of the George Washington University Medical Center. This program also ended by the mid 1980s.
In 1988, with the creation of a formal University Archives, University Archivist G. David Anderson began to conduct additional oral histories with the goal "To broaden and enrich the archival record of the University, supplementing the written record…. by recording on tape the recollections, impressions, attitudes and feelings of those associated with The George Washington University."
Other oral history special projects have included interviews with Foggy Bottom residents to coincide with the 200th anniversary of GW's presence in the neighborhood, and lengthy series of interviews with retiring GW Presidents Lloyd H. Elliot and Stephen J. Trachtenberg.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains consists primarily of oral histories conducted by or about George Washington University. The interviews exist in a variety of formats, including reel-to-reel tapes, audio cassette tapes, printed transcripts, digital files of transcripts, and digital recordings. Subjects covered by the interviews other than GW history include a school desegregation controversy in Montgomery County, Maryland in the 1970s; life experiences of long-term Foggy Bottom neighborhood residents; Washington, D.C. performing arts; and fair housing campaigns. The collection also includes interviews with Walter Fauntroy and Ari and Phyllis Kiev.
In addition to the interviews and transcripts, the collection includes administrative records related to the conduct of the interviews (correspondence, notes, etc.) as well as administrative records related to the various oral history projects represented in the collection.
Finally, the collection includes a significant amount of documentary material on school desegregation and the Rosemary Hills controversy, such as pamphlets, flyers, small publications, and newspaper clippings, that were intended to support the use of the related oral histories as a teaching collection. A detailed inventory of these items is located in Box 16.
This collection also includes oral histories conducted by undergraduate GW students Spring 2013 course HIST2020W, "Washington, DC: History, Culture, and Politics," taught by Dr. Christopher Klemek. These interviews are with former and current residents of Foggy Bottom and Southwest and discuss the 20th century history of the neighborhoods.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Rosemary Hills school integration oral history and documentation project, George Washington University oral histories, Medical Center Oral History Committee, Foggy Bottom oral histories, and Miscellaneous oral histories and administrative files.
Restrictions on Access
Some interviews in this collection are closed due to a lack of a signed release from the interviewee. A very small number of additional interviews have signed releases with further restrictions. These restricted and closed interviews are noted at the item level in the finding aid.
Physical files and transcripts of closed interviews have been moved to red boxes with an "R" number, although the cassette and reel-to-reel recordings of the interviews remain interfiled with open interviews.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains audio recordings that are currently only stored on cassette or reel-to-reel tapes. Researchers who wish to access these recordings may be required to pay for their digitization, and will be provided with access to the digitized version. Please contact the Public Services Coordinator and Outreach Librarian at speccoll@gwu.edu for additional information about this process.
Oral history; Housing; Race relations; Audiotapes; Wolf Trap Foundation for the Performing Arts; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Montgomery County (Md.); School integration; George Washington University--History; Kayser, Elmer Louis; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Elliott, Lloyd H.
- Rosemary Hills school integration oral history and documentation project, 1972-1977; Series 1; 14 Linear Feet 7 full and 2 partial record center cartons, 1 document box, and 2 cassette tape boxes
  Conditions Governing Access
  Some interviews in this series are closed due to a lack of signed releases from the interviewees. Other interviewees signed releases but placed other restrictions on their interview's access or use. These restrictions are noted at the item-level.
  The workflow of the project appears to be that participants were contacted and preliminarily interviewed by telephone, then a formal interview recorded on cassette tapes was conducted, a reel-to-reel "master" copy of the cassette tapes was made, the interview was transcribed, and finally the interview transcription was sent to the interviewee for approval along with a release form, which may or may not have been returned. Additional transcripts were created by archives staff in the early 2000s. Due to this process, recordings, contact files, and sometimes transcripts are included in the series for interviews whose participants either did not return releases or explicitly refused to sign releases.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Copies of some of the interviews in this series were obtained from or placed in other repositories of oral histories. Whenever this occurred, it is noted in the interviewee file.
  Arrangement
  The series is intellectually arranged with the oral histories first (arranged alphabetically by interviewee last name) and the documentary sources after. Physically, the materials for a single interview (e.g., cassette tapes, reel-to-reel tape, and transcript) are spread across multiple boxes because they are stored according to format. Transcripts and files for interviews that are currently closed have been moved to box R1, although the recordings continue to be stored alongside those for open interviews.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials generated in the 1970s through the efforts of Mary Jo Deering and others who embarked on a project to create a documentary teaching collection, including oral histories and printed sources, on school integration. The collection took as its primary topic the "Model School" controversy at Rosemary Hills elementary school. Participants in the Oral History Workshop at George Washington University, run by Mary Jo Deering, interviewed school administrators, teachers, parents, activists, and students about their experiences soon after the events surrounding this desegregation controversy.
  The series consists of oral history recordings on reel-to-reel and cassette tapes, administrative and background files related to particular interviewees, interview transcripts, as well as publications, newspaper clippings, and other printed resources related to school desegregation. An item-level inventory of these printed materials exists in Box 16.
  - Loretta Argrett interviewed by Muriel L. Hanson, 1972 November 8; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s); 1 Cassettes (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 1, Side 1, Box 2, Cassette 1)
    Discussion of Rosemary Hills "model school" by parent.
  - Charles W. Ault interviewed by Barbara Pomeroy, 1976 November 17; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R1, Box 2, Cassette 2, Cassette 3)
    School integration in Cleveland, Ohio; civic leaders' attitudes toward integration; legal opinion on school integration plan
    Closed; can only be released with prior written consent of Charles Ault
  - Lynn Berkely interviewed by Jeannette Kidd, 1977 June 22; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 4, Cassette 5, Box 17, Reel 7, Side 1)
    Discussion of forced integration in Rosemary Hills Cluster
  - Braxton Boyd interviewed by Phyllis Hathaway, 1972 November 6; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box R1, Box 2, Cassette 6, Cassette 7, Box 1, Reel 10, Side 1)
    Interview closed due to lack of a signed release from Rev. Boyd.
  - Helga Butler interviewed by Jeannette Kidd, 1977 June 15; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 17, Reel 7, Box 2, Cassette 8)
    Discussion of integration at Rosemary Hills Primary School
  - Joanne Cashel interviewed by Phyllis Hathaway, 1972 November 14; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 9, Box 1, Reel 8)
    North Chevy Chase Elementary School and the "model school" controversy.
  - Lynn Chertkov interviewed by Peggy Bruton, 1972 October 19; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 10, Box 1, Reel 3, Side 1)
    Comments as Model School Director, Rosemary Hills Community Children's Center
  - Gwen Coffield interviewed by Susan Harris, 1972 November 6; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 10, Side 2, Box 2, Cassette 11)
    Comments on Rosemary Hills Community School
  - John Daly interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 June 1; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 12, Box 1, Reel 4, Side 1)
    Role of Area I Planner in development of Rosemary Hills "model school" plan
  - Michael Davidson interviewed by Peggy Bruton, 1972 October 23; 1 Reels; 2 folder(s); 1 Cassettes (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 3, Side 2, Box 2, Cassette 13)
    Children's attitudes toward school and proposal, student statements at open hearing.
  - Hamilton Davis interviewed by Susan Yowell, 1972 November 21; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 17, Reel 1, Box 2, Cassette 14)
    Background of Rosemary Hills situation and community reaction to "model school" plan
  - Lois Davis interviewed by Peggy Bruton, 1972 November 27; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 15, Box 17, Reel 5, Side 1)
    Discussion of Rosemary Hills parents' response to school superintendent's proposal for dealing with racial imbalance at Rosemary Hills; comments on her attitude as a black parent
  - Lois Davis interviewed by Jeannette Kidd, 1977 June 21; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 16, Cassette 17)
    More on her involvement as a black parent in the school integration controversy at Rosemary Hills
  - Rita Eisenberg interviewed by Muriel L. Hanson, 1972 November 16; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 8, Side 2, Box 2, Cassette 18)
    Discussion of the North Chevy Chase "model school"
  - Homer O. Elseroad interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 April 2; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 17, Reel 3, Box 2, Cassette 19, Cassette 20)
    Proposals (as Superintendent of Schools, Montgomery County) for dealing with racial imbalance at Rosemary Hills Elementary School; personal philosophy about school integrations; school system relations with other agencies of the County government
  - Meriam Flam interviewed by Kathleen Rich, 1973 March 22; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 21, Box 1, Reel 9, Side 2A)
    Rosmary Hills faculty's position on "model school" controversy.
  - Lois Gaillard interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 May 5; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 22)
    Involved in planning to overcome racial imbalance at Rosemary Hills Elementary School
  - Gilbert Gold interviewed by Muriel L. Hanson, 1972 November 15; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 5, Side 2, Box 2, Cassette 23, Cassette 24)
    Discussion of open housing strategies; comments on community involvement in school integration controversy; discussion of Rosemary Village Apartments as pioneer open housing units in Montgomery County.
  - Gilbert Gold interviewed by Muriel Hanson, 1976 June 21; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 17, Reel 6, Box 2, Cassette 25, Cassette 26)
    Manager of the Rosemary Village Apartments on the relationship between housing and hte school busing controversy in Montgomery County, Maryland
  - Samuel Goodman interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 May 9; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 7, Side 2, Box 2, Cassette 27)
    Role of the Montgomery County Public Schools' Department of Research in making plans to overcome Rosemary Hills Elementary Schools' racial imbalance
  - Jean Grambs interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1976 October 28; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 17, Reel 9, Box 2, Cassette 28, Cassette 29)
    School integration nationally and in the Maryland-Washington-D.C. area, especially in Montgomery County, Maryland; an educator's response to teaching in integrated schools, to the Brown decision, to educational testing, and to social science research on school integration
  - Alonzo Grigsby interviewed by Richard White, 1977 April 15; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R1, Box 2, Cassette 30)
    Interview is closed due to no release being located.
    Assistant principal of Suitland High School reminisces about Dunbar High School in Washington, D.C. in the 1940s.
  - Henry Hilburn interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 June 8; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 31, Box 1, Reel 5, Side 1)
    Functional responsibilities of the Planning Division; genesis of concerns about Rosemary Hills; problems of declining enrollment in down-county schools.
  - Dean Hill interviewed by Muriel Hanson, 1973 May 18; 1 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 32, Box 17, Reel 2, Side 1)
    Discussion of Rosemary Hills "model school" plan.
  - Tom Israel interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 July 12; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 33, Box 17, Reel 3, Side 1)
    Board of Education deliberations on proposal to close Rosemary Hills Elementary School and to create "model school;" comments on citizen reaction
  - E. Guy Jewell interviewed by Beryl Saylor, 1976 October 14; 4 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 2, Cassette 34, Cassette 35, Cassette 36, Cassette 37)
    Career with Montgomery County Public Schools; evolution of school system; comments on educational and political development; integrating black and white schools in the 1950s
  - Gerald Johnson interviewed by Pat Carter, 1976 April 21 and 28; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 13, Box 2, Cassette 38, Cassette 39)
    Principal of Rosemary Hills Elementary School 1974-
  - Gerald Johnson interviewed by Jeannette Kidd, 1977 June 28; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R1, Box 1, Reel 12, Box 2, Cassette 40)
    Interview closed because release not received from Gerald Johnson.
    Principal of Rosemary Hills Elementary School, 1974-
  - Margaret Jones interviewed by Anne Elsbree, 1973 June 29; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 3, Cassette 1, Cassette 2)
    Principal of Brannockburn Elementary school from 1959 to 1971 discusses black education in Montgomery County from segregated to integrated systems and the Bannockburn voluntary busing program 1968-1971
  - Edward Kabakjian interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1972 November 20 and 1973 February 26; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 3, Cassette 3, Cassette 4)
    Discussion of North Chevy Chase "model school"
  - David A. Kearns III interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1972 November 1; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 17, Reel 5, Side 2, Box 3, Cassette 5, Cassette 6)
    A perent's attitude to Rosemary Hills' "model school"
  - Mr. and Mrs. Richard Mattingly interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1972 November 21; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 17, Reel 2, Side 2, Box 3, Cassette 7, Cassette 8)
  - Donald Miedema interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 June 22; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 3, Cassette 9, Box 1, Reel 6, Side 1)
    Role of Deputy Superintendent of Schools, Montgomery County Public Schools
  - John Mohr interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 May 9; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 3, Cassette 10, Box 17, Reel 4, Side 1)
    Then-principal of North Chevy Chase Elementary School on role in "model school" controversy
  - Eugene Moran interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 March 15; 1 Reels; 1.5 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 6, Side 2, Box 3, Cassette 11, Cassette 12, Side A)
    Role of Assistant Superintendent for Area I, Montgomery Public Schools, in formation of "model school" concept.
  - Ken Muir interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 May 11; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 4, Side 2, Box 3, Cassette 13)
    Role of Director of Information, Montgomery County Public Schools, in Rosemary Hills "model school" controversy.
  - Michael Myles interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1972 October 30; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 1, Side 2, Box 3, Cassette 14, Cassette 15)
    Background on the Rosemary Hills "Model School" plan with a former president of the PTA.
  - Joan Nugent interviewed by Jeannette Kidd, 1977 June 7; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 3, Cassette 16)
    Participation in Kansas City voluntary Catholic school integration plan, 1967-1968
  - Tony and Molly Nugent interviewed by Jeannette Kidd, 1977 June 28; 2 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box R1, Box 3, Cassette 17, Cassette 18)
    Recollections of Kansas City voluntary Catholic school integration plan as students
    Interview is closed due to lack of release.
  - Doris Petranek interviewed by Kathleen Rich, 1973 May 17; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 9, Side 2B, Box 3, Cassette 19)
    Activity in "model school" development in North Chevy Chase
  - Nick Reyes interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1972 November 2; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R1, Box 3, Cassette 20, Cassette 21, Box 1, Reel 11, Side 2)
    Interview closed at instructions of Nick Reyes.
    Discussion of Rosemary Hills "model school" with an emphasis on participation in SABE, Spanish Americans for Better Education.
  - Anna Roberts (not interviewed), 1972 (Box R1)
    File is closed due to lack of signed release
    Planned interview which was never held formally. File contains summary of telephone interview with Mary Jo Deering on October 18, 1972 and an informal personal interview on October 25 at Mrs. Roberts' home. The contents of the latter present significant dissenting views.
  - Scott Rutherford interviewed by Jeannette Kidd, 1977 June 20 and 27; 1 Reels; 3 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box R1, Box 1, Reel 15, Box 3, Cassette 22, Cassette 23, Cassette 24)
    Involvement in Rosemary Hills desegregation action and Citizens for Integrated Schools.
    Interviews closed because no release received from Scott Rutherford
  - Joseph Tarallo interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 May 24; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 17, Reel 4, Side 2, Box 3, Cassette 25)
    Rose of Associate Superintendent for Administration, Montgomery County Public Schools, in Rosemary Hills "model school" developments
  - Virginia Thomson interviewed by Muriel L. Hanson, 1973 June 29 (Box R1)
    Interview is closed; tape was destroyed but transcript and correspondence retained.
    Teacher at North Chevy Chase Elementary School.
  - Pete Treibley interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 May 1; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 3, Cassette 26, Box 1, Reel 7, Side 1)
    Role of the Montgomery County Education Association in innovation within the school system and the "model school" controversy
  - Ruth Vail interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 March 14; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 3, Cassette 27, Cassette 28, Box 1, Reel 9, Side 1)
    Origins of "model school" concept by Ruth Vail and her recruitment of other teachers into a planning team; citizen reaction to plan and community involvement in establishment of "model school"
  - Frances Ventre interviewed by Peggy Bruton, 1972 November 9; 1 Reels; 2 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 2, Side 1, Box 3, Cassette 29, Cassette 30)
    Comments on community opinions on "model school" in North Chevy Chase, Maryland.
  - Janet Weiner interviewed by Pat Carter, 1976 August 4; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R1, Box 17, Reel 8, Box 3, Cassette 31)
    Parental response to Montgomery Cuonty Schools' plan to institute busing between Chevy Chase Elementary and Rosemary Hills Elementary for purposes of racial balance; organization of campaign opposing plan; attitudes toward integration and busing
    Interview is closed due to conditions placed on its access and use by Janet Weiner.
  - Ingrid Weise interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1973 April 2; 1 Reels; 1.5 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 11, Side 1, Box 3, Cassette 32, Cassette 12, Side B)
    Discussion with Director of Instruction, Area I, Montgomery Public Schools
  - William Yoffee interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1972 November 27; 1 Reels; 2 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box 11, Box 1, Reel 2, Side 2, Box 3, Cassette 33, Cassette 34)
    Discussion of the Parents' Committee for the "model" open school.
  - Recording titled "The Integration of Montgomery County Schools by Mary Jo Deering & Freddie Wiss", Spring 1977; 1 Reels (Box 17, Reel 10)
    Recording is closed until and unless contents can be reviewed for closed interview content.
  - Recording titled "Proposed housing development project in Old Anacostia", undated (Box 17, Reel 13)
    Marilyn and Jon final
  - Documentary collection on school desegregation, around 1972-1977; 3 Linear Feet 2 record center cartons (Box 9, Box 10)
    Contains the document portion of the collection on school desegregation, including the original item list and guide to the collection.